(light guitar music)
- [Instructor] Alright, what
is reactive programming?
So, this is kind of a
rather meaty topic today,
so the big thing about
reactive programming
is gonna be focusing on processing
asynchronous streams of data,
so we'll take in a stream of data
and process it asynchronously.
A good quote here by Gerard Berry,
French computer science guy,
"Reactive programs also maintain
"a continuous interaction
with their environment,
"but at a speed which is
determined by the environment,
"not the program itself.
"Interactive programs
work at their own pace,
"mostly deal with communication,
"while reactive programs
only work in response
"to external demands
"and mostly deal with
accurate interrupt handling.
"Real-time programs are usually reactive."
So, that's a fairly
comprehensive statement there
about reactive programming.
The big thing is that you wanna remember
that you're processing mainly events.
It's gonna be some type of
event or a stream of events
is what you're gonna be working with
in a reactive programming context.
So, a lot of common use cases
for reactive programming
are external service calls,
where you're calling out to somebody else,
or a highly concurrent message consumer.
Actually, they're starting
to do batch processing
with reactive programming,
where you have a batch of data
that you need to process,
and in the old day, you'd
put it on this big server
and just let it crank away.
Now, we're actually going
into a streaming mentality
and getting some nice
efficiencies out of that,
and one of the goals
of some of the frameworks
is to provide an abstraction
over it being asynchronous,
meaning that you, as the developer,
when you're working with these frameworks,
you're not really totally aware that it is
an asynchronous or synchronous application
that you're working with,
so it's easy to forget
that's actually happening
under the covers.
So, some core features
of reactive programming,
we already talked about data streams
and being asynchronous.
Another one is non-blocking.
Then, we also have backpressure
and failures as messages,
or some people call it
failures as first class citizens,
and we'll get into each
one of these coming up.
So, data streams, that's
kind of a nebulous term.
It can be just about anything.
It can be like mouse clicks,
mouse movements, or
other user interactions,
so this is pretty common
when you're working
with GUI applications, but it
can also be like JMS messages,
sending and receiving REST service calls,
monitoring a Twitter feed, stock trades,
processing a list of
data out of a database,
so a stream is just a sequence
of events ordered in time,
and these are events that
you wanna be listening to
and taking some type of actions.
So, asynchronous, the events
are captured asynchronously.
A function is defined to execute
when the event is emitted.
There's a different
function that you can use
when an error is emitted,
and then, finally, there's
a function that's defined
when the complete event is emitted,
so you might have just
like one item on your,
air quotes, data stream,
or you could have five items,
and then you get a done signal,
so these are all different functions,
and we'll see these coming in.
I'm just laying down some
concepts here right now.
An important piece of the picture
is the Gang of Four Observer Pattern,
so this is an iconic book, Gang of Four.
This is the observer pattern out of here,
and basically, you have a subject
and the processing that
we're gonna be seeing
with reactive programming
kinda is founded on this.
Not exactly, but fairly close to this,
so you'll have a subject
and then you'll have an observer.
That observer is gonna
take some type of action,
so the subject is going to change,
and then it will notify the observers,
so when the subject changes,
the observers get notified.
So, ReactiveX extended it.
They actually have a slogan saying that
it's observable done right,
so this is timeline.
You can see in the top left corner there,
they're talking about a timeline,
and those are events
that have been emitted by
the observable, and these
can be different things.
And then, they take some type of action,
and here, we're calling it a flip,
so we're doing some type of flip action,
and you can see, through time,
you have the stream of events
and you get a result on
the other side of it,
and then, in the bottom right, there,
we also have an event.
If, for some reason, that
observable terminates abnormally.
Now, in that center box
there, that transformation,
there's a lot that can
be happening with that.
You can subscribe to certain events.
You can say I want like every third event.
You can put a filter on
there before it gets down
to the bottom and the action is taken,
so this has a lot to do
with the Java 8 Streams API,
where you have a lot of interaction
of controlling what the
events are going through that.
Non-blocking is another key concept.
This is pretty complex,
but the basic concept is,
in blocking code, the code is gonna stop
and wait for more data,
so you could be reading from a disk
and you're gonna wait
for the disk to set up.
Non-blocking, in contrast,
it's gonna process what's available
and then ask the center to be notified
when more is available,
but the core concept here
is when you're non-blocking,
that task or that thread
is going to go on to something else,
wherein blocking, you're
gonna stop and block and wait.
Now, here's an example of a
typical multi threaded server,
so we have requests coming in,
and they're gonna get
blocked at certain points,
and they'll block and wait,
and traditionally, in the Java community,
we're thinking okay,
we have lots of cores,
lots of threads that we can use this,
and it's actually a good thing.
So, again, we have a thread
wait while the IO catches up,
and do something else with the
other threads on the server,
so it's fairly efficient.
It does scale pretty well,
and this is at a very, very low level,
and this has been
tradition for a long time.
And then what happened was,
really what grabbed the
community's attention,
was Node.js came out, and they don't have
much control over threads,
so they set up a event loop,
and in Node.js, if you block,
you really kill the system performance.
So, what happens is there's an event loop,
and they have a very small thread pool,
but they do all non-blocking,
so what happens is nothing waits.
It processes it right through,
and there's no threads waiting,
and they do put up a lot
of impressive numbers
in terms of performance.
I think that's when the Java
community really started going
hey, what's this non-blocking stuff?
Kinda makes sense to get into it,
so the way I kinda envision in my head is
you can move a lot of
traffic on a road like this,
but it's all stop and go,
so you're gonna be stop
and go, stop and go,
stop and go, but in a
non-blocking environment,
you have a very efficient,
speedy super highway,
where everything's
moving along efficiently.
So, let's take a look at this
in a more typical context,
so this is a web request.
So, we get a request that
comes in on the port.
Let's say we're posting
JSON-2 in a web service.
We're gonna parse that
JSON, probably with Jackson,
then go through some business logic,
and ultimately, we'll probably
make a call to the database.
The database is going to process it,
and then it's gonna return back.
We'll parse it back to JSON and
then return it on that port.
Now, it's important to
understand, I put red Xs here,
and in a traditional
sense, each one of these
is where blocking is gonna occur.
In the traditional Servlet
API, we have blocking in that.
Traditionally, in Jackson
parser, there's blocking in that.
Calling the database,
there's blocking in that,
so these are all instances
of where blocking occurs.
In a reactive system,
what's gonna happen is
that request is gonna come
in like a callable future,
and it will get passed along
until the last very minute,
probably about where we're
calling the database here,
and then we are gonna process that stream,
parse a JSON, call the
database in a reactive format,
so that thread of processing
will stay on the CPU longer
in one continuous chunk.
It's not gonna block,
stop, wait, then come back,
so the CPU is able to
handle that more efficiently
because it's sitting
there in the same context,
and it's not stopping and
waiting and stopping and waiting,
stopping and waiting.
Next up is back pressure, so
this is an important concept.
The subscriber is able to throttle data,
so you can set up, say,
give me 100 records
or give me 10 records or give
me 1,000 records at a time,
or elements, so this
is an important concept
to allow communication between
the subscriber and publisher.
And I put a little fire hose here,
so basically, in a reactive architecture,
you wanna wait to throttle things.
If the client is becoming overwhelmed,
you want to be able to back it down,
so in the states, we have a saying about
trying to drink from a fire hose.
Obviously, you don't wanna
be drinking from a fire hose.
That would be a bad idea.
Okay, the next up is failures as messages,
and exceptions are not gonna be thrown
in a traditional sense,
so if we're processing
a stream of data and we have
some type of function there,
if we threw an exception, it
would break the processing
of the stream of data.
Instead, we are gonna
gracefully handle the exceptions
through a handler function,
so we called out that before,
so this is a core concept that
we don't throw exceptions at,
but we do handle them gracefully
with a specific handler function
for when things to go wrong.
Now, a couple key take aways
that I want you to have
from this presentation
is reactive programming
is gonna focusing on
processing streams of data,
and it's not for everything.
So, traditional CRUD applications
are still alive and well.
There's times where you
just wanna be processing
a forum post, and that's perfectly fine,
so it's gonna be very
application specific.
You can do it.
I expect to see the community's probably
gonna start over-using it,
but the traditional CRUD applications
and what we're been
doing as Java developers,
still gonna work just fine.
As far as performance goes,
you can expect the system's probably
gonna gain some advantages,
but this area's still very
early and still evolving,
so you know, you do expect
to see performance gains
in terms of server efficiency,
but, like everything else
in terms of performance,
your mileage is gonna vary.