Alright we've been going through
a lot of PowerPoint slides in this section of the course.
Kind of apologize for that,
I find the slide decks get a little boring after a while.
But, we had to cover a lot of content
getting our heads around this reactive programming stuff.
So we've laid down a lot of groundwork here.
But now I wanna jump over to Intelli-J,
and we're gonna look at some hands-on examples.
This is really just to get our feet wet
with reactive programming.
So we're gonna look at the reactive types
within the Spring framework,
the monos and the fluxes,
and what I have is a pretty simple little project,
a couple data types,
and we're gonna go in and play around with those.
Now I will check all this into GitHub,
it's in a little sandbox collection of stuff that I have.
Go ahead, check it out, take a look.
I encourage you to play with it,
start getting used to working with these reactive objects,
this is an extension of the Java 8 streams,
so I'm not covering all that technology,
I'm not gonna cover it in detail,
but we are gonna be utilizing a lot going forward.
So the reactive types and the Java 8 streams
are very, very closely related,
and you use a lot of the same techniques,
but I think I got some fun examples here,
and again this is just to get our feet wet.
We're gonna go through,
and just start getting used to using these reactive types
that are available in Spring Framework 5.
Alright we've been talking a lot about reactive programming,
let's take an actual look at some examples,
and what I have is a little project that I have
a sandbox up on GitHub,
I'll leave a link to the project here for sure,
once I get it checked in,
you can see everything is green there, in Intelli-J,
meaning that it hasn't been
committed and pushed,
but I will definitely leave that in the course resources
so that you can see this example.
And what I have is a pretty simple example,
we've got two objects, just a person, and a person command,
so we just have first name, last name,
and I got a little helper method here
that we'll be using to get output, so,
we'll have the little pojo here say its name.
And of course we're using project (speaks softly)
so we have data, no arcs constructor,
all arcs constructor,
and then I have a command here, so,
to emulate a command object,
and we'll use that for some type transformations,
and I put a convenience method on there too,
with the constructor, to create a person command
from a person object, so,
nothing too exciting there.
Now let's take a look at the test.
And I wrote everything in test,
so we can go through a number of different examples here.
And you don't know,
if you've taken my courses in the past,
you know that I'm a Burn Notice fan,
so we have the characters from Burn Notice here,
Michael, Fiona, good old Sam, and Jesse,
and let's take a look at some of the examples here,
and the first one we're gonna look at
is just a mono test, and,
what this is doing here, is we created a new person,
person mono,
and we do mono and just,
and just is going to create a mono object
from the given object that you're working with.
So this gives us a person mono,
and if we want to get the person object
out of the mono,
we call the block method on it,
and that's gonna return back that person,
and now we can do a login.
I'll go ahead and run this little test here
so you can see the output of the example.
And we can see there that we did get Michael Weston
back from that test.
Now let's go ahead and take a look at the next test here,
and this case here, we're gonna use the map function
to return back that person,
so actually I'm gonna reformat that a little bit.
So, that's a little bit better formatting,
and in this case, map is a transformation object,
just like Java streams,
Spring reactive stuff has that map function,
so we're gonna do type transformation in that sample,
and again we're just gonna do, say name,
and we'll go ahead and run this,
and we should see Fiona in the output.
And again, you need to remember
that we are calling this block function here,
and that's what triggers it,
because really this is essentially a future,
and it won't execute until something blocks on it.
Now, next up here, let's take a look at a filter example,
bring that up to the top of the screen,
and in this case, what we're gonna do
is filter out that mono,
so we're gonna do a stream,
so we'll get a stream on that,
and we're gonna say, hey, I'm asking for Foo,
and we're gonna take the Sam object,
and when I run this, we'll get a null pointer exception,
because they're gonna filter that,
and no results are gonna be back, so,
that person is gonna be a null object, or null, so,
in this case, this guy's gonna toss
a null pointer exception, which it does,
in J unit here, on line 47,
where it's saying I expect a null pointer to come back.
In all these examples so far,
we've been looking at mono.
So let's take a look at a flux.
And remember a flux is
multiple objects.
So a mono, just to reiterate, a mono is zero or one,
where a flux is zero or many.
So in this case here, let's go ahead and take,
run the flux test,
you see that he runs pretty quick.
Again, just like mono, we are using a flux,
and it can take in multiple properties,
so a couple different ways of creating the fluxes,
but here, you can see that we did get the flux,
and when we subscribed on it,
we are passing on the log info,
and we are getting our log output here
from the flux objects.
So collapse this guy, and let's take a look at the next one.
Now here we can also test a filter,
which I did not,
let me pause this.
Okay, I realized I forgot to put in a filter option on this,
so I went and did that real quick,
and what we're gonna do is filter on persons,
basically for Fiona.
Let's go ahead and run this now, make sure that works.
We can see that we only get Fiona, so,
we still had, just like in the example before,
we still had the four objects in there,
so we still had the four objects going into the flux,
but now we are doing a filter operation on it,
and we are gonna filter out just where Fiona is, and,
now here,
we can also do this,
and we're doing a delay,
so we're gonna emit every second here, and,
this is a little, little surprising,
if you're not used to streaming.
See how everything just went by?
And what happened there is that we're delaying,
but because it's running in the background,
we didn't wait for that output.
So it ran, and the test terminated
before that duration expired,
and a way around that when we're testing,
let me show you this here,
is to use a countdown latch,
and what we can do here,
is we're still gonna do a delay of one second,
but now on complete of that stream,
we are gonna count down that latch,
and this here on line 100
tells the test to wait until the countdown is complete.
So a handy way to do that,
and now if we run this,
and see that it's gonna go through,
and now we're gonna get the output every second,
and then the one last test that I wanna show you,
is we are gonna add in a filter,
so let's go ahead and run this guy,
and in this case, we'll just get Michael and Fiona,
because the others did not qualify,
so we're looking for a first name that contains I,
and you can see up here,
woops, scroll all the way up,
Michael and Fiona are the only ones.
Sam and Jesse do not match that criteria, so,
a number of different things that we can do with the
flux and the monos, the reactive types,
it's a lot of fun.
It's a little bit different,
it takes a little bit of getting your head around it, but,
I wanted to record this video,
and just show you some examples of these in action,
and I hope you found this video helpful.